<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Participation | Marlon E. Cobos</title><link>https://marlonecobos.github.io/tag/participation/</link><atom:link href="https://marlonecobos.github.io/tag/participation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Participation</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://marlonecobos.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Participation</title><link>https://marlonecobos.github.io/tag/participation/</link></image><item><title>Science Engagement</title><link>https://marlonecobos.github.io/mentoring/engagement/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://marlonecobos.github.io/mentoring/engagement/</guid><description>&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">I firmly believe that bridging the gap between scientific research and the wider community is essential. Through my work and well thought communication strategies, I aim to ignite curiosity and foster a deeper appreciation for science among people of all ages. Whether it is sharing my research findings with a broader audience, participating in outreach programs, or mentoring aspiring young scientists, I see science engagement as a two-way street. It not only enriches the public&amp;rsquo;s understanding of the world but also enriches my own perspective, reminding me of the real-world impact and importance of research. In this exciting journey, I hope to inspire others to join me in the thrilling pursuit of knowledge and discovery.&lt;/p>
&lt;br>
&lt;h3 id="engagement-activities">Engagement activities&lt;/h3>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">&lt;em>Outreach (Broader Impacts):&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Microbes on the move&lt;/strong>. &lt;em>Activities:&lt;/em> Review of Spanish translations of existing outreach materials; Spanish translations of social media posts; general outreach activities in places visited. &lt;em>Scope:&lt;/em> Three cities in the state of Kansas. Biodiversity Institute, &lt;em>University of Kansas&lt;/em>. Kansas, USA. July, 2022&lt;/p>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">&lt;em>Environmental education program:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Battery disposal awareness campaign&lt;/strong>. &lt;em>Activities:&lt;/em> Design of content and teaching materials for primary schools; Presentation of contents and educational activities in primary schools with the involvement of teachers and students. &lt;em>Scope:&lt;/em> Ten rural schools. &lt;em>El Guismi DAG&lt;/em>. Zamora Chinchipe, Ecuador. 2012-2013&lt;/p>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">&lt;em>Environmental education program:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Plastic bottle recycling campaign&lt;/strong>. &lt;em>Activities:&lt;/em> Design of content and teaching materials for primary schools; Presentation of contents and educational activities in primary schools with the involvement of authorities, teachers, and students. Design of mechanisms to collect, store, and recycle collected materials. &lt;em>Scope:&lt;/em> Ten rural schools. &lt;em>El Guismi DAG&lt;/em>. Zamora Chinchipe, Ecuador. 2012-2013&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>