<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Bio | Marlon E. Cobos</title><link>https://marlonecobos.github.io/tag/bio/</link><atom:link href="https://marlonecobos.github.io/tag/bio/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Bio</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://marlonecobos.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Bio</title><link>https://marlonecobos.github.io/tag/bio/</link></image><item><title>More about me</title><link>https://marlonecobos.github.io/post/more_about_me/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://marlonecobos.github.io/post/more_about_me/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="who-am-i">Who am I?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">I am an early career scientist originally from Ecuador, now settled in the United States. My roots trace back to Zamora Chinchipe, a small province in the southernmost part of the Amazon region, but the majority of my life story unfolded in Loja, a picturesque city nestled in the Andes to the south.&lt;/p>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">My academic journey commenced at Universidad Nacional de Loja (Ecuador), followed by a detour to Universidad de La Habana (Cuba) for my master&amp;rsquo;s degree. The culmination of my educational pursuits was marked by obtaining my Ph.D. from the University of Kansas (USA). Currently, I am engaged in postdoctoral research at the University of Kansas, where I divide my time between the Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology and the Biodiversity Institute.&lt;/p>
&lt;br>
&lt;h2 id="family">Family&lt;/h2>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">The cornerstone of my life undoubtedly rests upon my family&amp;rsquo;s unwavering love and support. Their presence has exerted an irreplaceable influence on every facet of my journey. My achievements owe much to their profound impact, and these words and milestones serve as a heartfelt expression of gratitude for the profound enrichment they have brought to my life.&lt;/p>
&lt;br>
&lt;h2 id="what-do-i-like">What do I like?&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="research">Research&lt;/h3>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">Research occupies a central place in my life. While those close to me might jest that I am entirely consumed by my work, the truth is more nuanced. Indeed, my deep-seated passion for science might give the impression that I am wholly devoted to my job, but what truly fuels me is the exploration of the scientific realm. My passion lies in delving into the mysteries of science, unraveling fresh research problems, and pursuing their solutions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">My research interests span a diverse array of topics, all converging within the fascinating field of distributional ecology. My quest revolves around understanding the determinants of species&amp;rsquo; geographic distributions. This curiosity leads me to engage in various research avenues. One of my primary interests involves crafting innovative methods and tools to construct models capable of characterizing ecological niches and predicting species distributions. Furthermore, I have a keen interest in assessing the broader context, such as predicting potential disease outbreaks and pandemics. The challenge of comprehending the factors that could precipitate an epidemic is akin to tackling an intricate puzzle, a pursuit that resonates deeply with my identity as a scientist.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="sports-and-friends">Sports and friends&lt;/h3>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">In my earlier years, sports held a significant place in my life. I dedicated numerous years to basketball and even participated in various leagues in Ecuador. However, in recent times, my engagement with sports has shifted towards recreational enjoyment, especially when shared with friends. Although I still enjoy shooting hoops, my leisure time is primarily devoted to volleyball and ping pong.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="hobies">Hobies&lt;/h3>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">Beyond my scientific endeavors, my leisure time is often occupied by my hobbies. Electronics and the art of tinkering hold a special appeal for me. There is an inexplicable satisfaction in assembling and fine-tuning intricate systems to perfection. Over the years, my interests in this domain have cultivated a fascination with tools, leading to the amassing of a comprehensive collection that some might consider excessive for my pursuits. Nevertheless, this toolset ensures that I am always well-prepared to tackle the next exciting project that comes my way.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>