<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ENM | Marlon E. Cobos</title><link>https://marlonecobos..github.io/tag/enm/</link><atom:link href="https://marlonecobos..github.io/tag/enm/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>ENM</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://marlonecobos..github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>ENM</title><link>https://marlonecobos..github.io/tag/enm/</link></image><item><title>enmpa</title><link>https://marlonecobos..github.io/software/enmpa/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://marlonecobos..github.io/software/enmpa/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="what-is-enmpa">What is enmpa?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">&lt;strong>enmpa&lt;/strong> comprises a set of tools to perform Ecological Niche Modeling using presence-absence data and logistic generalized linear models. Some of the main functions help perform data partitioning, model calibration, model selection, variable response exploration, and model projection.&lt;/p>
&lt;br>
&lt;h2 id="check-the-enmpa-package">Check the enmpa package&lt;/h2>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">If you want to try this tool you can install it on R from GitHub using &lt;code>remotes::install_github(&amp;quot;Luisagi/enmpa&amp;quot;)&lt;/code>. An example of its use can be found &lt;a href="https://github.com/Luisagi/enmpa#enmpa-ecological-niche-modeling-for-presence-absence-data" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;br></description></item><item><title>ellipsenm</title><link>https://marlonecobos..github.io/software/ellipsenm/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://marlonecobos..github.io/software/ellipsenm/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="what-is-ellipsenm">What is ellipsenm?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">&lt;strong>ellipsenm&lt;/strong> is an R package that implements multiple tools to help in using ellipsoid envelopes to model ecological niches of species. Handy options for calibrating and selecting models, producing models with replicates and projections, and assessing niche overlap are included as part of this package. Other functions implemented here are useful to perform a series of pre- and post-modeling analyses. A good reference of it use in research is &lt;a href="https://escholarship.org/uc/item/4f00x5r6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nuñez et al. (2021)&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;img src="featured.gif" align="center"/>
&lt;h2 id="check-the-ellipsenm-package">Check the ellipsenm package&lt;/h2>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">If you want to try this tool you can install it on R from GitHub using &lt;code>remotes::install_github(&amp;quot;marlonecobos/ellipsenm&amp;quot;)&lt;/code>. An example of its use can be found &lt;a href="https://github.com/marlonecobos/ellipsenm#ellipsenm-an-r-package-for-ecological-niches-characterization-usingellipsoids" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;br></description></item><item><title>kuenm</title><link>https://marlonecobos..github.io/software/kuenm/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://marlonecobos..github.io/software/kuenm/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="what-is-kuenm">What is kuenm?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">&lt;strong>kuenm&lt;/strong> is an R package designed to make the process of model calibration and final model creation easier and more reproducible, and at the same time more robust. The aim of this package is to design suites of candidate models to create diverse calibrations of Maxent models and enable selection of optimal parameterizations for each study. Other objectives of this program are to make the task of creating final models and their transfers easier, as well to permit assessing extrapolation risks when model transfers are needed. Check the reference in &lt;a href="https://peerj.com/articles/6281/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Cobos et al. (2019)&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;br>
&lt;h2 id="check-the-kuenm-package">Check the kuenm package&lt;/h2>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">If you want to try this tool you can install it on R from GitHub using &lt;code>remotes::install_github(&amp;quot;marlonecobos/kuenm&amp;quot;)&lt;/code>. An example of its use can be found &lt;a href="https://github.com/marlonecobos/kuenm#kuenm-an-r-package-for-detailed-development-of-maxent-ecological-niche-models" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;br></description></item><item><title>A simulation-based method for identifying accessible areas as calibration areas for ecological niche models and species distribution models</title><link>https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication/10.21425-f5fbg48814/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication/10.21425-f5fbg48814/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">Ecological niche models and species distribution models (ENM and SDM, respectively) are tools that have seen massive use and considerable improvement during the last twenty years. The choice of calibration areas for such models has strong effects on model outcomes and model interpretation, as well as on model transfer to distinct environmental settings. However, approaches to selecting these areas remain simple and/or unlinked to biological concepts. Such models should be calibrated within areas that the species of interest has explored throughout its recent history, the accessible area (&lt;strong>M&lt;/strong>). In this paper, we provide a simulation approach for estimating a species’ &lt;strong>M&lt;/strong> considering processes of dispersal, colonization, and extinction in constant current climate or glacial-interglacial climate change frameworks, implemented within a new R package we developed called grinnell. Using the avian genus Aphelocoma, we explored different parameterizations of our simulation, and compared them to current approaches for &lt;strong>M&lt;/strong> selection, in terms of model performance and risk of extrapolation using the algorithm Maxent and mobility-oriented parity analyses. Model calibration exercises from all approaches resulted in at least one model meeting optimal performance criteria for each species; however, we noted high variability among taxa and &lt;strong>M&lt;/strong> selection methods. More importantly, &lt;strong>M&lt;/strong> hypotheses derived directly from simulations of key biological processes, rather than being based on simple proxies of those processes, and as such are better suited to erecting biologically appropriate contrasts in model calibration, and to characterizing the potential for model extrapolation more rigorously. Major factors in our simulations were environmental layer resolution, dispersal kernel characteristics, and the inclusion of a changing framework of climatic conditions. This contribution represents the first simulation-based method for selecting calibration areas for ENM and SDM, offering a quantitative approach to estimate the accessible area of a species while considering its dispersal ability, along with patterns of change in environmental suitability across space and time.&lt;/p>
&lt;br></description></item><item><title>Recognizing sources of uncertainty in disease vector ecological niche models: An example with the tick Rhipicephalus sanguineus sensu lato</title><link>https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication/10.1016-j.pecon.2020.03.002/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication/10.1016-j.pecon.2020.03.002/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">Epidemiology is one of many fields that use ecological niche modeling to assess potential distributions or potential range expansions of species. When such models are transferred in space and time, it is important to understand sources and location of uncertainty in their predictions. Here, we used the tick species Rhipicephalus sanguineus sensu lato (distributed in different areas around the world) as an example; for the first time, we characterized its global geographic distribution using ecological niche modeling, and explore the uncertainty involved in transferring models in space and time. We assessed uncertainties based on risks of strict extrapolation and amounts and patterns of variation in our predictions. We integrated occurrence records and climate data to calibrate models for 5 world regions, and to project them to 11 general circulation models (GCMs) and two representative concentration pathway emissions scenarios (RCPs) for 2050. Models created in different calibration areas showed high agreement of suitable areas among model predictions from the eastern United States, southern Mexico, South America, Europe, North Africa, sub-Saharan countries, Asia, and Australia. The global potential distributions of R. sanguineus sensulato were very similar between the two RCPs, but GCMs, model replicates, and model parametrizations contributed importantly to the overall variation detected. Patterns of uncertainty (strict extrapolation areas and variation) in our model predictions depended on the calibration area, and underlined the important implications of not considering variability and extrapolation risk in interpretations of ecological niche model projections.&lt;/p>
&lt;br></description></item><item><title>kuenm: An R package for detailed development of ecological niche models using Maxent</title><link>https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication/10.7717-peerj.6281/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication/10.7717-peerj.6281/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">Background Ecological niche modeling is a set of analytical tools with applications in diverse disciplines, yet creating these models rigorously is now a challenging task. The calibration phase of these models is critical, but despite recent attempts at providing tools for performing this step, adequate detail is still missing. Here, we present the kuenm R package, a new set of tools for performing detailed development of ecological niche models using the platform Maxent in a reproducible way. Results This package takes advantage of the versatility of R and Maxent to enable detailed model calibration and selection, final model creation and evaluation, and extrapolation risk analysis. Best parameters for modeling are selected considering (1) statistical significance, (2) predictive power, and (3) model complexity. For final models, we enable multiple parameter sets and model transfers, making processing simpler. Users can also evaluate extrapolation risk in model transfers via mobility-oriented parity (MOP) metric. Discussion Use of this package allows robust processes of model calibration, facilitating creation of final models based on model significance, performance, and simplicity. Model transfers to multiple scenarios, also facilitated in this package, significantly reduce time invested in performing these tasks. Finally, efficient assessments of strict-extrapolation risks in model transfers via the MOP and MESS metrics help to prevent overinterpretation in model outcomes.&lt;/p>
&lt;br></description></item></channel></rss>