<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>R programming | Marlon E. Cobos</title><link>https://marlonecobos..github.io/tag/r-programming/</link><atom:link href="https://marlonecobos..github.io/tag/r-programming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>R programming</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://marlonecobos..github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>R programming</title><link>https://marlonecobos..github.io/tag/r-programming/</link></image><item><title>A simulation-based method for identifying accessible areas as calibration areas for ecological niche models and species distribution models</title><link>https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication/10.21425-f5fbg48814/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication/10.21425-f5fbg48814/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">Ecological niche models and species distribution models (ENM and SDM, respectively) are tools that have seen massive use and considerable improvement during the last twenty years. The choice of calibration areas for such models has strong effects on model outcomes and model interpretation, as well as on model transfer to distinct environmental settings. However, approaches to selecting these areas remain simple and/or unlinked to biological concepts. Such models should be calibrated within areas that the species of interest has explored throughout its recent history, the accessible area (&lt;strong>M&lt;/strong>). In this paper, we provide a simulation approach for estimating a species’ &lt;strong>M&lt;/strong> considering processes of dispersal, colonization, and extinction in constant current climate or glacial-interglacial climate change frameworks, implemented within a new R package we developed called grinnell. Using the avian genus Aphelocoma, we explored different parameterizations of our simulation, and compared them to current approaches for &lt;strong>M&lt;/strong> selection, in terms of model performance and risk of extrapolation using the algorithm Maxent and mobility-oriented parity analyses. Model calibration exercises from all approaches resulted in at least one model meeting optimal performance criteria for each species; however, we noted high variability among taxa and &lt;strong>M&lt;/strong> selection methods. More importantly, &lt;strong>M&lt;/strong> hypotheses derived directly from simulations of key biological processes, rather than being based on simple proxies of those processes, and as such are better suited to erecting biologically appropriate contrasts in model calibration, and to characterizing the potential for model extrapolation more rigorously. Major factors in our simulations were environmental layer resolution, dispersal kernel characteristics, and the inclusion of a changing framework of climatic conditions. This contribution represents the first simulation-based method for selecting calibration areas for ENM and SDM, offering a quantitative approach to estimate the accessible area of a species while considering its dispersal ability, along with patterns of change in environmental suitability across space and time.&lt;/p>
&lt;br></description></item><item><title>kuenm: An R package for detailed development of ecological niche models using Maxent</title><link>https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication/10.7717-peerj.6281/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication/10.7717-peerj.6281/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">Background Ecological niche modeling is a set of analytical tools with applications in diverse disciplines, yet creating these models rigorously is now a challenging task. The calibration phase of these models is critical, but despite recent attempts at providing tools for performing this step, adequate detail is still missing. Here, we present the kuenm R package, a new set of tools for performing detailed development of ecological niche models using the platform Maxent in a reproducible way. Results This package takes advantage of the versatility of R and Maxent to enable detailed model calibration and selection, final model creation and evaluation, and extrapolation risk analysis. Best parameters for modeling are selected considering (1) statistical significance, (2) predictive power, and (3) model complexity. For final models, we enable multiple parameter sets and model transfers, making processing simpler. Users can also evaluate extrapolation risk in model transfers via mobility-oriented parity (MOP) metric. Discussion Use of this package allows robust processes of model calibration, facilitating creation of final models based on model significance, performance, and simplicity. Model transfers to multiple scenarios, also facilitated in this package, significantly reduce time invested in performing these tasks. Finally, efficient assessments of strict-extrapolation risks in model transfers via the MOP and MESS metrics help to prevent overinterpretation in model outcomes.&lt;/p>
&lt;br></description></item></channel></rss>