<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>2 | Marlon E. Cobos</title><link>https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication-type/2/</link><atom:link href="https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication-type/2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>2</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://marlonecobos..github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>2</title><link>https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication-type/2/</link></image><item><title>A simulation-based method for identifying accessible areas as calibration areas for ecological niche models and species distribution models</title><link>https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication/10.21425-f5fbg48814/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication/10.21425-f5fbg48814/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">Ecological niche models and species distribution models (ENM and SDM, respectively) are tools that have seen massive use and considerable improvement during the last twenty years. The choice of calibration areas for such models has strong effects on model outcomes and model interpretation, as well as on model transfer to distinct environmental settings. However, approaches to selecting these areas remain simple and/or unlinked to biological concepts. Such models should be calibrated within areas that the species of interest has explored throughout its recent history, the accessible area (&lt;strong>M&lt;/strong>). In this paper, we provide a simulation approach for estimating a species’ &lt;strong>M&lt;/strong> considering processes of dispersal, colonization, and extinction in constant current climate or glacial-interglacial climate change frameworks, implemented within a new R package we developed called grinnell. Using the avian genus Aphelocoma, we explored different parameterizations of our simulation, and compared them to current approaches for &lt;strong>M&lt;/strong> selection, in terms of model performance and risk of extrapolation using the algorithm Maxent and mobility-oriented parity analyses. Model calibration exercises from all approaches resulted in at least one model meeting optimal performance criteria for each species; however, we noted high variability among taxa and &lt;strong>M&lt;/strong> selection methods. More importantly, &lt;strong>M&lt;/strong> hypotheses derived directly from simulations of key biological processes, rather than being based on simple proxies of those processes, and as such are better suited to erecting biologically appropriate contrasts in model calibration, and to characterizing the potential for model extrapolation more rigorously. Major factors in our simulations were environmental layer resolution, dispersal kernel characteristics, and the inclusion of a changing framework of climatic conditions. This contribution represents the first simulation-based method for selecting calibration areas for ENM and SDM, offering a quantitative approach to estimate the accessible area of a species while considering its dispersal ability, along with patterns of change in environmental suitability across space and time.&lt;/p>
&lt;br></description></item><item><title>Recognizing sources of uncertainty in disease vector ecological niche models: An example with the tick Rhipicephalus sanguineus sensu lato</title><link>https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication/10.1016-j.pecon.2020.03.002/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication/10.1016-j.pecon.2020.03.002/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">Epidemiology is one of many fields that use ecological niche modeling to assess potential distributions or potential range expansions of species. When such models are transferred in space and time, it is important to understand sources and location of uncertainty in their predictions. Here, we used the tick species Rhipicephalus sanguineus sensu lato (distributed in different areas around the world) as an example; for the first time, we characterized its global geographic distribution using ecological niche modeling, and explore the uncertainty involved in transferring models in space and time. We assessed uncertainties based on risks of strict extrapolation and amounts and patterns of variation in our predictions. We integrated occurrence records and climate data to calibrate models for 5 world regions, and to project them to 11 general circulation models (GCMs) and two representative concentration pathway emissions scenarios (RCPs) for 2050. Models created in different calibration areas showed high agreement of suitable areas among model predictions from the eastern United States, southern Mexico, South America, Europe, North Africa, sub-Saharan countries, Asia, and Australia. The global potential distributions of R. sanguineus sensulato were very similar between the two RCPs, but GCMs, model replicates, and model parametrizations contributed importantly to the overall variation detected. Patterns of uncertainty (strict extrapolation areas and variation) in our model predictions depended on the calibration area, and underlined the important implications of not considering variability and extrapolation risk in interpretations of ecological niche model projections.&lt;/p>
&lt;br></description></item><item><title>kuenm: An R package for detailed development of ecological niche models using Maxent</title><link>https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication/10.7717-peerj.6281/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication/10.7717-peerj.6281/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">Background Ecological niche modeling is a set of analytical tools with applications in diverse disciplines, yet creating these models rigorously is now a challenging task. The calibration phase of these models is critical, but despite recent attempts at providing tools for performing this step, adequate detail is still missing. Here, we present the kuenm R package, a new set of tools for performing detailed development of ecological niche models using the platform Maxent in a reproducible way. Results This package takes advantage of the versatility of R and Maxent to enable detailed model calibration and selection, final model creation and evaluation, and extrapolation risk analysis. Best parameters for modeling are selected considering (1) statistical significance, (2) predictive power, and (3) model complexity. For final models, we enable multiple parameter sets and model transfers, making processing simpler. Users can also evaluate extrapolation risk in model transfers via mobility-oriented parity (MOP) metric. Discussion Use of this package allows robust processes of model calibration, facilitating creation of final models based on model significance, performance, and simplicity. Model transfers to multiple scenarios, also facilitated in this package, significantly reduce time invested in performing these tasks. Finally, efficient assessments of strict-extrapolation risks in model transfers via the MOP and MESS metrics help to prevent overinterpretation in model outcomes.&lt;/p>
&lt;br></description></item><item><title>Major challenges for correlational ecological niche model projections to future climate conditions</title><link>https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication/10.1111-nyas.13873/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication/10.1111-nyas.13873/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p style="text-align: justify;">Species-level forecasts of distributional potential and likely distributional shifts, in the face of changing climates, have become popular in the literature in the past 20 years. Many refinements have been made to the methodology over the years, and the result has been an approach that considers multiple sources of variation in geographic predictions, and how that variation translates into both specific predictions and uncertainty in those predictions. Although numerous previous reviews and overviews of this field have pointed out a series of assumptions and caveats associated with the methodology, three aspects of the methodology have important impacts but have not been treated previously in detail. Here, we assess those three aspects: (1) effects of niche truncation on model transfers to future climate conditions, (2) effects of model selection procedures on future-climate transfers of ecological niche models, and (3) relative contributions of several factors (replicate samples of point data, general circulation models, representative concentration pathways, and alternative model parameterizations) to overall variance in model outcomes. Overall, the view is one of caution: although resulting predictions are fascinating and attractive, this paradigm has pitfalls that may bias and limit confidence in niche model outputs as regards the implications of climate change for species’ geographic distributions.&lt;/p>
&lt;br></description></item><item><title>Open access solutions for biodiversity journals: Do not replace one problem with another</title><link>https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication/10.1002-aqc.2967/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://marlonecobos..github.io/publication/10.1002-aqc.2967/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;ol style="text-align: justify;">
&lt;li>Global change processes (including climate change, sea‐level rise, and land‐use change, among others) represent significant threats to biodiversity. These changes are usually studied across broad areas, and understanding their effects on narrowly distributed endangered species is challenging. &lt;em>Peltophryne florentinoi&lt;/em> is a critically endangered Cuban toad, restricted to two coastal localities and potentially threatened by these phenomena. Despite its endangered status, few analyses have focused on threats to its survival in the face of global change.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Current and future threats from global change to this species were evaluated using ecological niche modelling and multiscale geographic information system (GIS) approaches. Climate change effects were assessed by comparing the species niche with six future (2050) climate scenarios across its distribution area. Risks from sealevel rise were evaluated by simulating potential coastal inundation under three scenarios of sea‐level rise. Recent land‐use changes were quantified using information on the loss of forest cover between 2000 and 2015.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Within the species distribution area, warmer and drier conditions can be expected in the future. Sea‐level rise will not have direct impacts on the species range; however, occasional inundations and saltwater intrusion may present additional stressors. Although only ~2% of the forest cover has been lost in the species range and its surroundings during 2000–2015, deforestation trends were variable during this period, and future losses in forest cover can be expected.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Considering these threats, and that the colonization of new areas seems unlikely, indirect and additive adverse effects on the species can be anticipated. These impacts will most probably be observed during the larval stage of this toad; hence, breeding sites constitute a key element in the conservation of this species. Longterm studies and experimental manipulations may be the next steps towards a better understanding of the responses of P. florentinoi to expected changes. Initial conservation actions are proposed based on these results and the ecology of this species.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;br></description></item></channel></rss>